Guide to the William Ernest Henley Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Ernest Henley Collection
1736-1941
1878-1902
GEN MSS 1131
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(12 boxes)
Henley, William Ernest, 1849-1903
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, printed material, and ephemera relating to the life and work of the writer William Ernest Henley. Correspondents include Robert Fitzroy Bell, his future wife Anna Nancy Boyle, and Robert Louis Stevenson.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings by dates of accession: I. 1946-1980 Acquisitions. II. 1986-1995 Acquisitions. III. 2001-2004 Acquisitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 1946-2004. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
William Ernest Henley (1849-1903)
William Ernest Henley was a British poet, editor, and critic whose friends included Rudyard Kipling and Robert Louis Stevenson. His works include A Book of Verses (1888), London Voluntaries (1893), and Hawthorn and Lavender (1899).
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Photographs -- England -- 19th century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Bell, Robert Fitzroy; Henley, Anna Nancy Boyle; Henley, William Ernest, 1849-1903; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894
- 1946-1980 Acquisitions, 1878-1901; 1
  - Letters from William Ernest Henley
    - ALS to "Dear A. M.", 1896 November 8 (Box 1)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchased from Kingston Galleries on the Library Associates Fund, 1965.
    - 5 ALS to Charles Baxter, [1879?], 1881 (Box 1)
      Purchased from C. A. Stonehill on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1980.
    - ALS to William H. Brett, 1878 February 22 (Box 1)
      Gift of Bernhard Knollenberg, 1946
    - ANS to [James Nicol] Dunn, 1895 August 1 (Box 1)
      Gift of James Marshall Osborn, 1950.
    - ALS to [Hind?], 1897 November 16 (Box 1)
      Removed from Dean Brodie... (London: D. Nutt, 1892)
    - ALS to Dr. and Mrs. Hutchinson, 1892 April 22 (Box 1)
      Removed from Henley's Song of the Sword (London: David Nutt, 1892).
    - ALS to George P. Johnston, 1896 July 20 (Box 1)
      Purchased from James Thin on the Plain Fund, 1956.
    - 14 ALS to David Nutt, 1894-1896 (Box 1)
      Gift of G. C. Lilly, 1948.
    - AL, draft, signed with initials to Robert Louis Stevenson, 1888 May 7 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Accompanied by draft of a letter in the hand of Henley and Katharine Stevenson de Mattos to Robert Louis Stevenson, and by draft of a letter, in the hand of Katharine Stevenson de Mattos to Robert Louis Stevenson, both undated.
    - ALS To D. Thomson, 1892 November 14 (Box 1)
      Purchased from H. M. Fletcher on the Edwin F. Beinecke Book Fund, 1958.
    - AL to [Walter?] signed, W.E.H., 1901 January 12 (Box 1)
      Removed from Hensley's Hawthorn and Lavender (London, 1901), the gift of Mr. and Mrs. W. Robert Blum, 1959.
    - ALS to Gleeson White, 1891 April 24 (Box 1)
      Purchased from I. K. Fletcher on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1962.
    - 6 ALS to various correspondents, 1895-1902 (Box 1)
      Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc., on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1959
    - 5 ALS to various correspondents, 1893-1901 (Box 1)
      Purchased from Kingston Galleries on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1967.
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, 1881 April 29 (Box 1)
      Puchased from H. M. Fletcher on the Beinecke Fund, 1958.
  - Writings
    - 2 notebooks, authograph manuscript draft of poems, with revisions, by William Ernest Henley, including Henley's two series, In Hospital and Life and Death, undated; 2 (Box 1)
      Purchased on the Library Associates Fund, 1962.
    - "Hospital Incidents," manuscript, by William Ernest Henley, in an unidentified hand, undated (Box 1)
    - "Maternal Ancestry," typescript, by Robert Louis Stevenson, with corrections in Henley's hand., undated (Box 1)
      Accompanied by a short history of Henley's childhood in an unidentififed hand.
- 1986-1995 Acquisitions, 1872-1902; 2
  - 1986 Acquisition
    Purchased from Hofmann & Freeman on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1986.
    - Fifty-two autograph letters signed from Henley to Fitzroy Bell, 1889-1899, undated; 8 (Box 2)
  - January 1991 Acquisition
    Purchased from Pickering & Chatto on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1991.
    - Autograph letters signed from Henley to Anna Nancy Boyle, 1876-1877, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - July 1991 Acquisition
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1991.
    - Autograph letter signed from Henley to Mr. Nutt, undated (Box 4)
  - September 1991 Acquisition
    Purchased from William Reese Co., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1991.
    - 5 notebooks containing autograph manuscript extracts from works of Choderlos Laclos, Lope de Vega, Nicolo Machiavelli and others, as well as miscellaneous notes by Henley, 1872-1874; 5
    - 3 notebooks containing manuscript extracts from works by Heinrich Heine, Victor Hugo, and other notes and writings by Henley, 1874-1899; 3 (Box 5)
  - 1993 Acquisition
    Purchased from David A. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1993.
    - 2 ALS to [Alfred] Austin from Henley, 1891 June 18 and October 22 (Box 6)
    - 5 ALS to A. G. Dew-Smith from Henley, 1887-1892 (Box 6)
    - "Bare Ruined Quires," manuscript in an unidentified hand, 1902 (Box 6)
  - 1995 Acquisition
    Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1995.
    - 4 ALS to John W. Gilman from Henley, 1896-1902 (Box 6)
- 2001-2004 Acquisitions, 1736-1941; 3
  - February 2001 Acquisition
    Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2001.
    - Song of Speed galley proofs, corrected in an unidentified hand; with two copies of the publication (London: David Nutt, 1903), clipping and menu card, 1901-1903 (Box 7)
    - 45 ALS to [Anna Boyle] from Henley, 1875-1877 (Box 7)
  - February 2001 Acquisition
    Purchased from John Hart on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2001.
    - Typed copy of letter to W. E. Henley from Robert Louis Stevenson, dated 1894 July 15, undated (Box 8)
    - 2 telegrams to William Ernest Henley and Mrs. Henley from Arthur Morrison and "J.W.G" sending anniversary greetings, and 1 telegram to Mrs. Henley from Gertrude and Vernon Blackburn expressing condolences, presumably on the death of her husband., 1903 January, July (Box 8)
    - Music scores, autograph manuscript, in an unidentified hand, for "The Last Whistle," and "Ave Caesar", undated; 2 (Box 8)
    - Henley bookplates designed by William Nicholson, 1898 (Box 8)
    - Autograph manuscript, in an unidentified hand, of pages of a draft of an unidentified playscript, undated (Box 8)
    - Printed poems by W. E. Henley, 1893, undated (Box 8)
    - "Matri Dilectissimae," printed poem by W. E. Henley, for a memorial service, 1902 (Box 8)
    - Memorial cards for Margaret Mackie Bonle and Margaret Emma Henley, 1886, 1894 (Box 8)
    - Mrs. W. E. Henley visiting cards, undated (Box 8)
    - Scrapbook containing press clippings relating to the Glasgow Lyrical Society, 1862-1902 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. K. G. Richmond and solicitors in Edinburgh and London regarding papers of W. M. Henley, 1930 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1890-1941 (Box 8)
    - Publisher's flyers for Henley's A Book of Verses, a list of David Nutt's publications, and a printed list of the officers and committe members of the Incorporated Society of Authors, Playwrights and Composers, undated (Box 8)
    - Xenophon: His Ageslaus with Other Opuscula by H. G. Dakyns, corrected page proofs, bound, with autograph note by Dakyns presenting the book to Henley laid in, 1902 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous printed items, 1857-1901 (Box 8)
    - Photographs of W. E. Henley and family members and friends, most unidentified, circa 1880-1900; 7 (Box 9)
    - Album of newspaper clippings of review of Henley's book "A Book of Verses", 1888 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Photograph and prints of the bust of Heny by Rodin, circa 1908 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Pages from disbound scrapbook containing newspaper and magazine clippings regarding the life and death of Lord Byron, 1736-1824 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Photograph case, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook containing several newspaper clippings regarding Rudyard Kipling's poem, "The Islanders", 1902 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - July 2001 Acquisition
    Purchased from Michael Silverman on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
    - 2 ALS from William Ernest Henley to R. Fitzroy Bell, 1895, 1896 (Box 12)
  - July 2004 Acquisition
    Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the Hall Park McCullough Fund, 2004.
    - "Hospital Outlines: Sketches and Portraits" by William Ernest Henley, proof and 3rd corrected proof, 1875 April 25, June 15 (Box 12)
  - August 2004 Acquisition
    Purchased from Christopher Edwards on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004.
    - 18 ALS to William George Hutchinson from William Ernest Henley, 1849-1903, undated (Box 12)
  - Copies of collection catalog cards (Box 12)